# Petar P. Raykov

RESEARCHER · PSYCHOLOGY

MRC Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit, Cambridge

#### **SUMMARY**

Early career cognitive psychologist with experience of working in academia (at post-doc level). I have worked on designing studies to examine the processes involved in episodic memory. Hands on experience with both M/EEG and fMRI data analysis. I am particularly interested in understanding brain mechanisms that support memory and how they are affected by aging. More recently, I have been interested in lifestyle factors that can contribute to healthy aging and longitudinal modelling.

#### **EDUCATION**

## **Sussex University**

Falmer, UK 2016-2019

PhD in Psychology (Funded by ESRC)

- Title: Neurobiology of specific and general prior knowledge
- Supervisors: Chris Bird & Jane Oakhill

# **University of Edinburgh**

Edinburgh, UK

MSc in Human Cognitive Neuropsychology (Distinction)

2015-2016

• Dissertation: Retrieval Orientation, Cognitive Control and Ageing (top in year).

## Loughborough University

Loughborough, UK

BSc Psychology (First Class Honours)

2011-2015

• *Dissertation*: Effects of manipulating expectancies after game play on cognitive performance.

## **PUBLICATIONS**

Raykov, P. P., Knights, E., & Henson, R. N., (2024). Does functional system segregation mediate the effects of lifestyle on cognition in older adults? *Neurobiology of Aging*, *134*, 126-134,

https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neurobiolaging.2023.11.009

Raykov, P. P., Varga, D., & Bird, C. M. (2023). False Memories for ending of events. *Journal of Experimental Psychology: General*, 152(12), 3459-3475, https://doi.org/10.1037/xge0001462

Varga, D., Raykov, P. P., Ben-Yakov, A., & Bird, C. M., (in prep). The surprising role of the hippocampus in processing prediction errors.

Raykov, P. P., Oedekoven, C. S. H., Keidel, J. & Bird, C. M. (in prep). Decreased inter-subject synchronization among people with mild cognitive impairment in the episodic memory network.

De Luca. F., Raykov, P. P., Berens, S. C., Ezzyat, Y., Davachi, L., & Bird, C. M., (in prep). Processing of goal-changes in narrative events.

Raykov, P. P.\*, Bromis, K.\*, Wickens, L., Roseboom, W., & Bird, C. M. (2022). The Neural Representation of Events Is Dominated by Elements that Are Most Reliably Present. *Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience*, *34*(3), 517-531, https://doi.org/10.1162/jocn\_a\_01802

- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J. L., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C. M. (2021). Activation of Person Knowledge in Medial Prefrontal Cortex during the Encoding of New Lifelike Events. *Cerebral Cortex*, 31(7), <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhab027">https://doi.org/10.1093/cercor/bhab027</a>
- Farooq, A., Raykov, Y. P., Raykov, P. P., & Little, M. A. (2022). Controlling for sparsity in sparse factor analysis models: adaptive latent feature sharing for piecewise linear dimensionality reduction. *Journal of Machine Learning Research* (accepted)
- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J. L., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C. M. (2019). The brain regions supporting schema-related processing of people's identities. *Cognitive neuropsychology*, 1-17. https://doi.org/10.1080/02643294.2019.1685958
- Raykov, P., P., Keidel, J. L., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C. M. (2018). Shared contextual knowledge strengthens inter-subject synchrony and pattern similarity in the semantic network. *eNeuro*. http://dx.doi.org/10.1101/276683

## **SELECTED PRESENTATIONS**

- Raykov, P., Daly J., & Bird, C (Apr 2023) Effects of APOE genotype on brain activity during movie watching (Poster). *British Neuroscience Association Festival of Neuroscience*.
- Raykov, P.P., Keidel, J., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C (Apr, 2021). Activation of Person Schematic Knowledge in MPFC (talk). *British Neuropsychological Society.*
- Raykov, P.P., Daly J., De Luca, F., Varga, D., & Bird, C (Nov 2021). Event Memory in young and old (Talk). Celebration of 60 years Sussex University. *House of Commons*
- Raykov, P. P., Bromis, K., Wickens, L., Roseboom, W., & Bird, C. M. (2021). Repeated and predictable elements are dominating memory representations (poster). *Society for Neuroscience*
- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C (Apr., 2021). Schema knowledge in MPFC (poster). *British Neuroscience Association Festival of Neuroscience*.
- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C (Apr, 2018). Shared contextual knowledge strengthens inter-subject synchrony and pattern similarity (Poster). *The International Conference on Learning and Memory.* (Huntington Beach, CA, USA)
- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C (Nov, 2018). Prior knowledge and shared semantic representations (blitz talk) *British Neuropsychological Society*. (London, UK)
- Bird, C., Keidel, J., Raykov, P. P., Oedekoven, C. (Sep 2018). Importance of the ventromedial PFC for remembering complex events (Talk). *Memory Disorders Research Society*. (Toronto, Canada).
- Raykov, P. P., Keidel, J., Oakhill, J., & Bird, C (Sep, 2018). Shared representations across participants detected in the BOLD signal (Poster). *Interpreting BOLD: Furthering the dialogue between cellular and cognitive neuroscience.* (Oxford, UK)

Raykov, P.P., & Sienna, M., (Apr 2017). Proactive cognitive control, retrieval orientation and recollection selectivity (Poster). British Neuroscience Association Festival of Neuroscience. (Birmingham, UK)

#### **GRANTS AND SCHOLARSHIPS**

SeNSS Post-doctoral Fellowship (ESRC) £100,000 - Learning of Schemas and making sense of complex events. (2020-21)

Sussex Overseas Institutional Visits Grant (£ 1700) & Experimental Psychological Society (EPS) study visit grant (£2100), for a 2 month visit to Princeton University. (2018)

British Neuroscience Association Festival of Neuroscience 2023 - Poster award for open science.

Grindley Travel Grant to attend the Events in Memory Workshop, York (2017) Highly Commended Dissertation Award 2015/2016

UK/EU masters scholarship - 100, £10 000 scholarships divided across all MSc programmes (2015)

## **WORK EXPERIENCE AND RESPONSIBILITIES**

## Cognition and Brain Sciences Unit, University of Cambridge

Research Associate 2023 – present My work involves running experiments addressing how predicts affect memory

representations and analysing a large neuroimaging dataset, addressing how aging affects the brain and cognition. Specifically my focus is on how lifestyle factors can lead to improved health and cognition in late life.

# **University of Sussex**

Brighton, UK

Research Fellow & Doctoral tutor

2019 - 2023

My work involved designing and running imaging and behavioural studies investigating how prior knowledge affects memories. Involved in pre-registering, analysing and writing up of projects examining event segmentation. Providing supervision to PhD students and staff less experienced with advanced fMRI analyses.

# **Princeton University**

Princeton, USA

Study Visit

2019 - 2019

Visited the Princeton Computational Memory Lab, and Hasson lab at Princeton University. I was working on applying machine learning analysis techniques developed there to data I had collected at University of Sussex.

## **University of Sussex**

Brighton, UK

Programme Organizer

2017 - 2018

Arranging neuroimaging meetings and aid the documentation of upcoming projects. Regularly presenting seminars on advanced fMRI analyses.

# **Aston University**

Birmingham, UK 2013 - 2014

Research Assistant

Investigated cognitive inhibition in depression, through implementing both behavioural and neurophysiological (EEG) measures.

### **SKILLS**

Designing, Collecting and analysing fMRI and EEG studies. Advanced fMRI analyses: MVPA, ISC, ISPS, ISFC, ICA, HMM, and various functional connectivity methods. Advanced Matlab (incl. SPM, Cogent and machine learning methods), Python (incl. scikit-learn, nilearn and brainiak), R, SPSS, Bash scripting, FSL, Basic AFNI, Basic Cluster Computing and system management, Java, HTML and SQL for running online experiments, E-prime, Multi-level modelling, Factor analysis, Non-parametric statistics, Multivariate statistics, Microsoft Office, Photoshop and Various video and audio editing software.